Thomas Barrett and Leni Mancuso papers relating to William Kienbusch
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Thomas Barrett and Leni Mancuso papers relating to William Kienbusch
1950-1979, 2002
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Barrett, Thomas R.
0.2 linear feet
The Thomas Barrett and Leni Mancuso papers relating to William Kienbusch measure 0.2 linear feet and date from 1950 to 1979 and 2002. The 113 letters and postcards from William Kienbusch to Barrett and Mancuso document their long friendship and describe in great detail Kienbusch's life as an artist in New York and Maine. Also found are 15 snapshot photographs of Keinbusch, Barrett, and Mancuso outdoors.
Provenance
The collection was donated in 2002 by Thomas R. Barrett and Leni Mancuso.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art are the William Kienbusch papers, 1915-2001; the Walter Maitland correspondence with and about William Kienbusch, 1969-1981; the William Kienbusch letters to Francis and Sydney Hamabe, 1958-1977; and an oral history interview with William Kienbusch conducted by Forrest Selvig, November 1-7, 1968.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
William Kienbusch (1914-1980) was a painter and art instructor in New York, NY, and Cranberry Island, Maine. Kienbusch enjoyed a long friendship with painters Thomas Barrett and Leni Mancuso. Mancuso studied painting with Kienbusch at the Brooklyn Museum Art School. Barrett and Mancuso spent most of the year in Maine and often went on summer painting trips to the coastal islands with Kienbusch.
Scope and Content Note
The Thomas Barrett and Leni Mancuso papers relating to William Kienbusch measure 0.2 linear feet and date from 1950 to 1979 and 2002. The 113 letters and postcards from William Kienbusch to Barrett and Mancuso document their long friendship and describe in great detail Kienbusch's life as an artist in New York and Maine. Also found are 15 snapshot photographs of Keinbusch, Barrett, and Mancuso outdoors.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 2 series:
Series 1: Letters from William Kienbusch, 1950-1979, 2002 (Box 1; 8 folders)
Series 2: Photographs, 1953-1958, 1966, 2002 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Kienbusch, William, 1914-1980
Subjects-Topical:
Painters--Maine; Painters--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Postcards
Names:
Kienbusch, William, 1914-1980; Mancuso, Leni
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Letters from William Kienbusch, 1950-1979, 2002, Series 1:; (Box 1; 8 folders)
  Found here are 113 letters and postcards from William Kienbusch to Thomas Barrett and Leni Mancuso. Also included is a typed inventory of the letters written by Thomas Barrett in 2002. Kienbusch's detailed letters discuss his life as an artist, his health, and his perspectives on his contemporaries. He often makes references to exhibitions in New York City, lectures, openings, personalities, and changes in the direction of art from 1950 to 1980. Letters were written while Kienbusch was in New York, Maine, and while traveling abroad in Madrid, Athens, and Nepal.
  - Inventory of Letters, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Photographs, 1953-1958, 1966, 2002, Series 2:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  Fifteen snapshot photographs document William Kienbusch's outdoor sketching trips with Thomas Barrett and Leni Mancuso at locations such as Hurricane Island, Maine, and Nova Scotia. Also found here is an inventory written by Thomas Barrett in 2002 which includes dates and brief descriptions of each photograph.
  - Inventory of Photographs, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, 1957-1958, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)